{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In 2005, this figure offered his resignation to Larry Lucchino and walked out in a gorilla suit. In 2002, this man was hired for a job that had been turned down by Billy Beane, as described at the end of Moneyball. Tom Ricketts hired this man as President in 2011; with Jed Hoyer, this man brought Anthony Rizzo and Kris Bryant to Wrigley Field. For ten points, name this baseball executive who, as GM and President, ended the World Series droughts of both the Boston Red Sox and Chicago Cubs.",
      "answer": "Theo Epstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man formulated Operation Paukenschlag, part of a military plan also known as the “Second Happy Time.” This man issued a command to disregard drowning sailors after the a B-24 bomber attacked a ship carrying survivors of the Laconia. This head of state under the Flensburg government pioneered “wolfpack” tactics in the Battle of the Atlantic. For ten points, name this admiral who advocated for unlimited U-boat warfare, then surrendered to the Allies after he was named Adolf Hitler’s successor as President of Germany.",
      "answer": "Karl D¨onitz"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was prompted by faulty intelligence that claimed one side was at Fort Ninety-Six. While attempting to taunt the enemy commander, William Washington had his horse shot out from under him. In this battle, John Eager Howard helped form one of three lines of defense set up by the Broad River to repel an attack from the British Legion under Banastre Tarleton. For ten points, name this 1781 Revolutionary War victory for Daniel Morgan in South Carolina.",
      "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
    },
    {
      "question": "The action at the center of this case was first defined in Stromberg v. California, while the ruling of Bethel v. Fraser was held to be distinct from this case. Abe Fortas’s majority opinion in this case held that the action in question did not cause a disruption and that its participants did not lose their rights “at the schoolhouse gate.” This case dealt with five children who, in 1965, wore black armbands to protest the Vietnam War in Iowa. For ten points, name this Supreme Court case that protected students’ right to free speech.",
      "answer": "Tinker v. Des Moines Independent Community School District"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man worked to quell the revolt of Francis Rakoczi while working as president of the Imperial War Council. This man commissioned the Belvedere Palace after his victory at the Battle of Zenta, which led to the Treaty of Karlowitz and the Ottoman withdrawal from Central Europe. In 1704, this general joined up with the Duke of Marlborough to defeat the Duc de Tallard at the Battle of Blenheim. For ten points, name this Habsburg commander during the War of the Spanish Succession.",
      "answer": "Prince Eugene of Savoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this family became the first woman appointed to the Harvard University faculty and fought typhoid in Chicago from Hull House. Another member of this family served as the Headmistress of the Bryn Mawr college prep school in Baltimore for 26 years, then detailed the “Timeless Tales of Gods and Heroes” in a 1942 work whose first section teaches about Greek creation myths. For ten points, name this family, including public health advocate Alice and classicist Edith, the author of Mythology.",
      "answer": [
        "Hamilton",
        "Alice and/or Edith Hamilton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A Western offshoot of this group coalesced around “general” Charles Kelly. Part of this group under William Hogan stole a Northern Pacific train, prompting Montana marshals to intervene. This group dispersed shortly after its leader was arrested for trespassing on the White House lawn. An Ohio businessman led this group, officially called the Army of the Commonwealth in Christ. For ten points, name this group of unemployed workers that marched on Washington following the Panic of 1893.",
      "answer": [
        "Coxey’s Army",
        "Army of the Commonwealth in Christ before mentioned",
        "“Army” not needed after mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At this location, Ahmad Abdali’s forces defeated Sadashivrao Bhau, though the Durrani Empire opted to retreat regardless. After a victory at Tughlaqabad, Hemu was killed at a battle in this location when Bairam Khan moved to reconquer Delhi. At one battle in this location, one ruler used araba carts to maximize the effect of his artillery against Ibrahim Lodi. For ten points, name this site of a 1526 victory for Babur that marked the beginning of the Mughal dynasty.",
      "answer": "Battles of Panipat"
    },
    {
      "question": "This mathematician names an exact solution to the Einstein field equation describing swirling dust. He spent time in a sanitarium for a nervous breakdown following the murder of Moritz Schlick by Johann Nelbock, who was pardoned after two years by the Nazis. This mathematician is best known for showing that axiomatic systems cannot prove their own consistency and that all axiomatic systems with a notion of arithmetic will contain unprovable truths. For ten points, give this mathematician who names a set of two incompleteness theorems.",
      "answer": "Kurt G¨odel"
    },
    {
      "question": "A city in this present-day country along the Irtysh River was the capital of the self-proclaimed Alash Autonomy and was the home of a facility nicknamed “The Polygon. The Semipalatinsk nuclear test site is in this country, as is a location leased until 2050 by its northern neighbor where Sputnik I was launched. This home of the Baikonur Cosmodrome moved its capital from Almaty in 1997. Astana is now the capital of, for ten points, what former Soviet republic, the largest landlocked country in the world?",
      "answer": "Republic of Kazakhstan"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man replaced his superior, Quintus Caecilius Metellus, as the commander of the expedition against Jugurtha. He decisively defeated the Cimbri and the Teutones while serving as consul, a position that he was elected to seven times. In an effort to minimize the baggage train, this man ordered his soldiers to carry their supplies on his back, earning them the nickname of this man’s mules. For ten points, name this Roman general, the first to recruit soldiers from the poor, one of his many military reforms.",
        "answer": "Gaius Marius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marius’s rival late in life was this man, the first general to march on Rome. He instituted proscription to target his political enemies.",
        "answer": "Lucius Cornelius Sulla Felix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2006, 11 people in this country’s town of Ishaqi in Balad province were killed and their house blown up; cables released by Wikileaks indicate that U.S. forces were responsible for that incident. Camp Speicher, an air force base in this country’s city of Tikrit, was attacked by ISIS in 2014, killing over 1,500 Shia cadets. In 2007, George W. Bush ordered a “surge” of troops into, for ten points, what Middle Eastern country invaded by U.S. forces in 2003?",
        "answer": "Iraq"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Employees of this private security company, which has since been renamed XE Services and Academi, killed 17 people in the 2007 Nisour Square massacre in Baghdad; four of its guards were convicted of manslaughter or murder.",
        "answer": "Blackwater"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Poland was forced to exit this war following the Treaty of Altranstadt, which also provided for the execution of the nobleman Johann Patkul. Shortly after a naval engagement at Grengam, this conflict was ended through The Treaty of Nystad. During this conflict, the Cossack leader Ivan Mazepa joined forces with Charles XII, only to be defeated by the forces of Peter the Great. For ten points, name this 18th century conflict in which Russia defeated the Swedish empire.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ivan Mazepa and Charles XII alliance at this 1709 battle failed to overcome Peter the Great’s forces, and Sweden failed to recover. After this battle, Carl Gustav Rehnskiold was captured and Charles XII fled to the Ottoman Empire.",
        "answer": "Battle of Poltava"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1833 court case originating in this state held that the restrictions in the Bill of Rights did not apply to state governments and was launched after a diversion of water ruined John Barron’s wharf. This state was a party to a ruling in which a liberal interpretation of the Necessary and Proper Clause allowed the creation of a national bank; that ruling struck down this state’s tax on out-of-state banks. For ten points, name this state, which lost its suit against James McCulloch, head of a bank in its city of Baltimore.",
        "answer": [
          "Maryland",
          "McCulloch v. Maryland BONUS:InadditiontotheNecessaryandProperClause,JohnMarshall’srulinginMcCulloch v. Maryland made use of this Constitutional clause, which makes state laws subordinate to federal laws. ANSWER: Supremacy Clause",
          "Article VI, Clause Two of the Constitution"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hall of Bulls is found at this Paleolithic cave complex in France. it also includes a drawing of a bird-headed figure being impaled by a bison.",
        "answer": "Lascaux caves"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom faced a religious uprising that was led by Beatriz Kimpa Vita and named for Saint Anthony. A ruler of this kingdom, Henrique, was made Bishop of Utica. The first European to meet with this kingdom was Diogo C˜ao [cow] in 1482, after which its king took the name Jo˜ao. After a failed 1914 revolt, this kingdom’s monarchy was abolished and its land assimilated into the colony of Angola. For ten points, name this kingdom that converted to Christianity after meeting the Portuguese and which names a pair of countries in Central Africa.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Kongo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Kingdom of Kongo was discovered by Portuguese sailors who used these small ships on missions of exploration. They had lateen sails and were much smaller than galleons.",
        "answer": "caravels"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Early settlers to what is now this state relied on the Ocracoke Inlet for their shipping routes. Its sand dunes at Jockey’s Ridge are the tallest on the East Coast. Settlers of a colony in this state disappeared with only the word “Croatoan” carved into a tree as evidence, and its Kill Devil Hills were the site of the first controlled flight of the Wright Brothers. Kitty Hawk is located on the Outer Banks of, for ten points, what state, home to Roanoke Island and the city of Raleigh?",
        "answer": "North Carolina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of the Outer Banks are protected by a national seashore named for this cape, whose lighthouse was moved inland in 1999 in response to the beach’s erosion.",
        "answer": "Cape Hatteras"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This activity, when conducted in a morally incorrect way, was condemned as “nefas” by the Ancient Romans. Augustine used Romans 13:4 to support this activity when conducted by the church. The School of Salamanca attempted to develop a theory of this activity based on Thomas Aquinas’ three conditions for its justification. The rights of jus in bello and jus ad bellum both involve this activity. For ten points, name this general term for an armed conflict between societies.",
        "answer": "war"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to numerous religious discussions on war, this Prussian military theorist described war as the “continuation of politics by other means” in his secular treatise On War.",
        "answer": "Carl von Clausewitz"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Maine",
      "prompt": "In the history of Maine, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Other state, the site of Lexington and Concord, originally controlled Maine’s territory?",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "War, the colonial phase of the Seven Years’ War, included a raid on Woolwich, Maine?",
          "answer": "French and Indian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "1863 Civil War battle included the defense of Little Round Top by the 20th Maine?",
          "answer": "Battle of Gettysburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "WarwascausedbyaborderdisputeinvolvingMaineloggersandwasendedbytheWebster-Ashburton Treaty?",
          "answer": "Aroostook War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry included the Lewiston-Auburn strike and the development of mills in Freeport?",
          "answer": [
            "textile industry",
            "clothing industry",
            "shoemaking",
            "garment manufacturing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician was nicknamed the “magnetic man” and the “continental liar from the state of Maine?”",
          "answer": "James Gillespie Blaine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Female senator from Maine delivered the anti-McCarthyist “Declaration of Conscience” speech?",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Chase Smith",
            "either underlined name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American peoples, whose name calls their home “Dawnland,” once lived in present-day Maine?",
          "answer": [
            "Wabanaki Peoples",
            "Abenaki Peoples"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Pompey the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival of Pompey who became dictator of Rome before his assassination in front of a statue of Pompey.",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of outlaws that targeted Roman shipping and which Pompey fought in the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "pirates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title held by Pompey three times, the highest elected position in Rome.",
          "answer": "consul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Celebration undertaken by Pompey three times, granted when soldiers acclaimed their general as imperator.",
          "answer": "triumph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ally of Pompey and member of the First Triumvirate who died fighting the Parthians at the Battle of Carrhae.",
          "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region that Pompey conquered from Mithridates the Great. It was home to the Kingdoms of Pontus and Bithynia on the eastern end of Rome’s territory.",
          "answer": [
            "Asia Minor or Anatolia",
            "Pontus if given before you read it"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman law that gave Pompey the power to defeat the aforementioned Mediterannean outlaws.",
          "answer": "Lex Gabinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellious general in Hispania that Pompey fought at the beginning of his career. He successfully waged a guerrila war against Rome.",
          "answer": "Quintus Sertorius"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Figures in Philippine History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Former Mayor of Davao City and current President of the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Rodrigo Duterte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Combat sport mastered by Filipino Senator Manny Pacquiao [pack-ee-ow].",
          "answer": [
            "boxing",
            "word forms, like boxer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Fashion item of which former First Lady Imelda Marcos collected hundreds of pairs.",
          "answer": "shoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who led during the Spanish-American War and retained the Philippines thereafter.",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "First President of the Philippines, who fought until 1901 against the United States.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary author of Noli Me Tangere who was executed in 1896 by the Spanish.",
          "answer": "Jos´e Rizal"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female President, who succeeded Ferdinand Marcos after the People Power Revolution.",
          "answer": "Corazon Aquino"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second female President, who was acquitted of lottery theft in 2016.",
          "answer": "Gloria Macapagal Arroyo"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was reinforced by Eurymedon and Demosthenes, though their men failed to breach the Epipolae walls. A lunar eclipse convinced one side to linger in a harbor during this event, leaving them exposed to attack from (20 pts)",
        "Gylippus. The destruction of the Hermai statues shortly before this campaign led to the recall of one of its leaders, (10 pts)",
        "Alcibiades [al-sih-by-ah-deez]. For ten points, name this disastrous campaign of the Peloponnesian War in which Athens tried to invade a large Mdeiterranean island."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sicilian Expedition",
        "equivalents for expedition, like Campaign"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. The 2006 film Long Road to Heaven describes this event and the ensuing trials of Amrozi and Imam Samudri, who were executed in 2008 for their roles in it. One part of this event was allegedly triggered by Dulmatin’s (20 pts)",
        "cell phone. A group led by Riduan Isamuddin perpetrated this event, in which a Mitsubishi L300 loaded with C4 was detonated outside Paddy’s Pub and the (10 pts)",
        "Sari Club. Over 200 people were killed in this event, which was carried out by members of Jemaah Islamiyah, a terrorist group based in Southeast Asia. For ten points, name this 2002 bombing, the deadliest terrorist attack in Indonesian history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "2002 Bali bombing",
        "other descriptors"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A prologue involving the Rumor family was cut from one of this man’s compositions; Rudolph Giuliani led a protest of a 2014 staging of that work. A work by this man opens with the “Chorus of Exiled Palestinians” and “Chorus of Exiled Jews” and depicts the (20 pts)",
        "hijacking of the MS Achille Lauro. Another of his operas features the aria “News has a kind of mystery” and centers on a (10 pts)",
        "1972 visit to Mao Tse-Tung. For ten points, name this American composer of The Death of Klinghoffer and Nixon in China, who shares his name with multiple U.S. presidents."
      ],
      "answer": "John Coolidge Adams"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man hosted a religious debate at his castle of Azuchi, which he built to defend the capital. He used arquebuses against a cavalry attack at the Battle of Nagashino, and he defeated an Imagawa attack into his territory at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Okehazama. After the treachery of Akechi Mitsuhide, this man was forced to commit suicide in the Incident of Honnoji. (10 pts)",
        "Toyotomi Hideyoshi succeeded, for ten points, which daimyo who overthrew the Ashikaga Shogunate, the first “Great Unifier” of Japan during the Sengoku period?"
      ],
      "answer": "Oda Nobunaga"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, the Minnesota was struck by stray cannon fire from the James River Squadron. During the battle, an explosion blinded Captain John Worden with paint, forcing his ship to withdraw. In this battle, the (20 pts)",
        "USS Congress and Cumberland were destroyed in an attempt to stop the Anaconda Plan. Catesby ap Roger Jones led the second day of this engagement, in which (10 pts)",
        "neither ship suffered significant damage. For ten points, name this Civil War naval battle, the first combat between two ironclad ships."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hampton Roads",
        "descriptions of the battle between the USS Monitor and the USS Merrimack,",
        "between the USS Monitor and the CSS Virginia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a novel, this historical figure laments seeing Venus for the last time on December 17th after a voyage along the Magdalena River. This man’s personal papers were edited by Daniel O’Leary. This author of the Cartagena (20 pts)",
        "Manifesto is the subject of Gabriel Garcia Marquez’s novel The General in His Labyrinth; that book is set after he resigned the presidency of (10 pts)",
        "Gran Colombia in 1830. For ten points, name this South American independence leader, nicknamed “The Liberator.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Shortly after this city was defeated at Tebas, its king Yusuf I requested aid from the Marinids to fight the Battle of Tarifa. When this city’s king Boabdil was forced into exile, he allegedly looked back wistfully at this city at a mountain pass now known as the (20 pts)",
        "“Moor’s sigh.” The Nasrids established a kingdom in this city shortly after the Battle of Las Navas de Tolosa. This city’s (10 pts)",
        "Alhambra fortress was captured during the Reconquista. For ten points, name this city, the former capital of a Muslim emirate in southern Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Granada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man gave a press conference that opened with John Quinn quoting Ben Franklin’s “A republic, sir, if you can keep it” anecdote. Later in the press conference, this man discussed a tax deduction for giving his (20 pts)",
        "Vice Presidential papers to the government and misspoke, suggesting that John Ehrlichman was guilty until proven innocent. The press conference climaxed with this man explaining “I have (10 pts)",
        "earned everything I have got” after noting that “people have got to know whether or not their President is a crook.” For ten points, name this President who was grilled by newspaper editors in 1973 over the Watergate scandal."
      ],
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    }
  ]
}